A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of Reports, Information Files FA1714
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of Reports, Information Files
1936-1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1714
1.1 Cubic Feet 3 letter document containers
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into one series: Information Files from the Office of the Director.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as part of Accession 2019:079 (Box 35390).
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of information files culled from the Ford Foundation's Office of Reports. These information files consist of correspondence, reports, and program assessment materials that were originally housed in the Director's Office within the Office of Reports.
Ford Foundation -- History
- Information Files from the Office of the Director, 1936-1981; 1
  - Ford Foundation Historical Materials - Notes on the Principles and Policies of the Ford Foundation (Second Draft), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Copy #8
  - Ford Foundation Historical Materials - Mr. McKeever Special Docket (First Draft), 1955 August (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ford Foundation Historical Materials - Statements of Grants, 1936-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ford Foundation Historical Materials - Background Articles, 1953-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Draft article by David Cohn, September 1953
    How the Ford Foundation Works (Edited Third Draft), T. Keenan, April 1961
    Seminar Document - The Ford Foundation - Its Interest in Community Development, January 1956
    Information Bulletin No. 44 - Fact Sheet, January 1956
  - Docket - Meeting of the Trustees - Part 1: The President's Report, 1953 May 13-14 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Ford Foundation Historical Financial Report, 1936 January 15-1954 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation Organizational Charts, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Ford Foundation Management and Program Trends in the Fifties and Sixties, 1971 June (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ford Foundation Self-Study, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Special Program in Education "Most-Favored Universities", 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Special (Slater) Committee, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ford Foundation 25th Anniversary Materials, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Food/Agriculture, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Foundation Relations with Government Programs, 1965-1972 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Trustees Statement, 1964 August-September (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Fund for Area Planning, 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "The Ford Philanthropies, 1911-1936," William Greenleaf - Correspondence and Draft, 1956-1963 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Humanities and the Arts - Ford Foundation Program, 1957-1963 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Individual Grants Manual, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 20)